Guide to the H. Lee Waters Film Collection, 1936-2005, bulk 1936-1942 RL.10075
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Movies of Local People, 1936-1942; 50 Linear Feet
  - Roxboro (N.C.)
    - 1939 (Reel 1), TRT 00:35:12
      - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 25, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0209)
      - Preservation tape master, betacam sp (Box 30, Video-cassette RL10075-Bcam-0015)
      - Preservation tape master, betacam sp, duplicate (Box 30, Video-cassette RL10075-Bcam-0016)
      - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic (Box 31, Video-cassette RL10075-Umatic-0018)
      - Shot list. (Box 34)
    - circa 1940 (Reel 1), TRT 00:43:09
      - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Oversize-film-can 1, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0009)
      - Color separation, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 8, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0072)
      - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 17, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0147)
      - Color separation negative, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 17, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0148)
      - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 25, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0210)
      - Preservation tape master, betacam sp (Box 30, Video-cassette RL10075-Bcam-0017)
      - Preservation tape master, betacam sp, duplicate (Box 31, Video-cassette RL10075-Bcam-0018)
      - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic (Box 31, Video-cassette RL10075-Umatic-0019)
      - Shot list. (Box 34)
    - circa 1941 (Reel 1), TRT 00:15:34
      - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 8, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0073)
      - Color separation, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 8, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0074)
      - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 17, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0149)
      - Color separation negative, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 17, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0150)
      - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 25, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0211)
      - Preservation tape master, betacam sp (Box 30, Video-cassette RL10075-Bcam-0017)
      - Preservation tape master, betacam sp, duplicate (Box 31, Video-cassette RL10075-Bcam-0018)
      - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic (Box 31, Video-cassette RL10075-Umatic-0020)
      - Shot list. (Box 34)
  - Rutherfordton (N.C.)
    - 1937 (Reel 1), TRT 00:14:45
    - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 9, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0077)
    - DVD master (Box 35, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0020)
  - Salisbury (N.C.)
    - 1940 (Reel 1), TRT 01:02:59
      - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 9, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0078)
      - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 18, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0152)
      - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 25, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0213)
      - Preservation tape master, digital betacam (Box 31, Video-cassette RL10075-Dbcam-0023)
      - DVD master (Box 35, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0021)
    - 1940 (Reel 2), TRT 00:16:45
      - Color separation, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 9, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0079)
      - Color separation negative, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 18, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0153)
      - Color separation print, 16 mm, si., col., reel 1 of 1 (Box 25, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0214)
  - Scotland Neck (N.C.)
    - 1939 (Reel 1), TRT 00:18:59
      - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 9, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0080)
      - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 18, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0154)
      - Preservation tape master, betacam sp (Box 31, Video-cassette RL10075-Bcam-0019)
      - Shot list. (Box 34)
  - Siler City (N.C.)
    - 1937-1939 (Reel 1), TRT 00:56:08
      - 16mm original B&W reversal, reel 1 of 2 (Box 37, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0225)
      - 16mm preservation estar B&W answer print, silent, reel 1 (Box 38, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0228)
      - 16mm preservation estar B&W dupe neg., reel 1 (Box 38, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0229)
      - Preservation tape master, digital betacam, reel 1 (Box 33, Video-cassette RL10075-Dbcam-0029)
        Sent to AV Geeks for migration to digital file, June 13, 2014. Returned from AVGeeks with raw video and MP4 files, June 27, 2014.
      - DVD master, reel 1 (Box 36, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0036)
      - DVD master, reel 1 (Box 36, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0037)
    - 1937-1939 (Reel 2), TRT 00:59:04
      - 16mm original B&W reversal, reel 2 of 2, section 1 (Box 37, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0226)
      - Digital 10-bit 2K preservation scan of reversal original RL10075-F16-0226 (Digital-materials RL10075-SET-0017, Video-file RL10075-F16-0226.mkv)
      - 16mm original color reversal, reel 2 of 2, section 2 (Box 37, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0227)
      - Digital 10-bit 2K preservation scan of reversal original RL10075-F16-0227 (Digital-materials RL10075-SET-0017, Video-file RL10075-F16-0227.mkv)
      - 16mm preservation estar B&W answer print, silent, reel 2 section 1 (Box 38, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0230)
      - 16mm preservation estar B&W dupe neg., reel 2 section 1 (Box 38, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0231)
      - 16mm preservation estar color answer print, silent, reel 2 section 2 (Box 38, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0232)
      - 16mm preservation estar color internegative, reel 2 section 2 (Box 38, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0233)
      - Preservation tape master, digital betacam, reel 2 (Box 33, Video-cassette RL10075-Dbcam-0030)
      - DVD master, reel 2 (Box 36, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0038)
      - DVD master, reel 2 (Box 36, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0039)
      - Digital 10-bit 2K preservation scan of reversal original RL10075-F16-0226 (Digital-materials RL10075-SET-0017, Video-file RL10075-F16-0226.mkv)
      - Digital 10-bit 2K preservation scan of reversal original RL10075-F16-0227 (Digital-materials RL10075-SET-0017, Video-file RL10075-F16-0227.mkv)
    - 1937-1942 (Reel 1), TRT 01:17:27
      - DVD master, from original 16mm (Box 35, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0022)
        Source: Milo Holt
  - Smithfield (N.C.) and Selma (N.C.)
    - 1937 (Reel 1), TRT 00:20:14
      - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 9, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0081)
      - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reels 1-2 of 2 (Box 18, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0155)
      - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic (Box 31, Video-cassette RL10075-Umatic-0022)
      - Shot list. (Box 34)
    - 1937 (Reel 2), TRT 00:20:04
      - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 9, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0082)
  - Spindale (N.C.)
    - 1937 (Reel 1), TRT 00:27:24
    - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 9, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0083)
    - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 18, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0156)
    - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 25, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0215)
    - Preservation tape master, digital betacam (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10075-Dbcam-0024)
    - DVD master (Box 35, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0023)
  - Statesville (N.C.)
    - 1940 (Reel 1), TRT 00:13:43
      - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 10, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0085)
      - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 18, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0157)
      - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 26, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0216)
      - Preservation tape master, digital betacam (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10075-Dbcam-0025)
      - VHS copy (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10075-Dbcam-0007)
      - DVD master (Box 35, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0024)
    - 1940 (Reel 2), TRT 00:15:28
      - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 10, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0086)
      - Color separation, 16 mm, si., col., reel 2 of 2 (Box 10, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0087)
      - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 18, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0158)
      - Color separation negative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 18, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0159)
      - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 26, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0217)
      - Color separation print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 26, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0218)
  - Swannanoa (N.C.)
    - 1938 (Reel 1), TRT 00:19:31
    - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 10, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0088)
    - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 19, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0160)
    - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 26, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0219)
    - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10075-Umatic-0023)
    - Preservation tape master, betacam sp (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10075-Bcam-0020)
    - Shot list. (Box 34)
  - Taylorsville (N.C.)
    - 1939 (Reel 1), TRT 00:25:24
    - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 10, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0089)
    - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 19, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0161)
    - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 26, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0220)
    - Preservation tape master, digital betacam (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10075-Dbcam-0026)
    - DVD master, from internegative (Box 35, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0025)
  - Thomasville (N.C.)
    - 1936-1940 (Reel 1), TRT 00:18:50
      - Digital 10-bit 2K preservation scan of reversal original RL10075-F16-0092 (Digital-materials RL10075-SET-0013, Video-file RL10075-F16-0092.mkv)
      - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 11, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0092)
      - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 19, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0163)
      - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 26, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0222)
      - Preservation tape master, digital betacam (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10075-Dbcam-0027)
      - DVD master, from internegative (Box 35, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0026)
    - 1936-1940 (Reel 2), TRT 00:15:52
      - Digital 10-bit 2K preservation scan of reversal original RL10075-F16-0093 (Digital-materials RL10075-SET-0013, Video-file RL10075-F16-0093.mkv)
      - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 11, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0093)
      - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 19, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0164)
      - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 26, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0223)
    - 1938-1939 (Reel 1), TRT 00:16:57
      - Digital 10-bit 2K preservation scan of reversal original RL10075-F16-0091 (Digital-materials RL10075-SET-0013, Video-file RL10075-F16-0091.mkv)
      - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 11, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0091)
      - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 19, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0162)
      - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 26, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0221)
      - Preservation tape master, digital betacam (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10075-Dbcam-0027)
      - DVD master, from internegative (Box 35, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0026)
  - Troy (N.C.)
    - 1936-1940 (Reel 1), TRT 00:50:16
      - Digital UHD preservation scan of preservation internegative RL10075-F16-0165 (Digital-materials RL10075-SET-0014, Video-file RL10075-F16-0165.253.avi)
      - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 19, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0165)
      - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic, reel 1 of 2 (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10075-Umatic-0024)
      - Preservation tape master, betacam sp, reel 1 of 2 (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10075-Bcam-0021)
      - Preservation tape master, betacam sp, duplicate, reel 1 of 2 (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10075-Bcam-0022)
      - Shot list. (Box 34)
    - 1936-1940 (Reel 2), TRT 00:44:45
      - Digital UHD preservation scan of reversal original RL10075-F16-0166 (Digital-materials RL10075-SET-0014, Video-file RL10075-F16-0166.254.avi)
      - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 19, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0166)
      - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic, reel 2 of 2 (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10075-Umatic-0025)
      - Preservation tape master, betacam sp, reel 2 of 2 (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10075-Bcam-0023)
      - Preservation tape master, betacam sp, duplicate, reel 2 of 2 (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10075-Bcam-0024)
      - Preservation tape master, digital betacam, duplicate, reel 2 of 2 (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10075-Dbcam-0028)
  - Whitmire (S.C.)
    - circa 1938-1939 (Reel 1), TRT 00:17:05
    - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 11, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0094)
    - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 19, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0167)
    - Screening print, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 1 (Box 26, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0224)
    - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic (Box 33, Video-cassette RL10075-Umatic-0026)
    - Preservation tape master, betacam sp (Box 33, Video-cassette RL10075-Bcam-0025)
    - DVD master (Box 36, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0034)
    - DVD master dupe (Box 36, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0035)
    - Shot list. (Box 34)
  - Winnsboro (S.C.), 1936; 71
    Screening Date: 1936 December 04. Screening Theatre: unknown.
    - VHS copy (Box 36, Video-cassette RL10075-VHS-0005)
  - Wytheville (Va.)
    - circa 1939 (Reel 1), TRT 00:15:35
      - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 11, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0095)
      - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 1 of 2 (Box 19, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0168)
      - Preservation tape master, 3/4 inch Umatic (Box 33, Video-cassette RL10075-Umatic-0027)
      - Preservation tape master, betacam sp (Box 33, Video-cassette RL10075-Bcam-0026)
      - DVD master (Box 35, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0027)
      - Shot list. (Box 34)
    - circa 1939 (Reel 2), TRT 00:18:13
      - Reversal original, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 11, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0096)
      - Internegative, 16 mm, si., b&w, reel 2 of 2 (Box 19, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0169)
  - Trailer for Movies of Local People, circa 1960
    Trailer for bringing Movies of Local People back to their local theaters in the late 1950s/early 1960s.
    - Original 35mm print, 50 film feet (Box 33, Film-reel RL10075-F35-0001)
- Associated Audiovisual Materials
  - Home movies, 1930s; 1400 film feet
    - Digital 2K+ preservation scan of reversal original RL10075-F16-0246 (Digital-materials RL10075-SET-0015, Video-file RL10075-F16-0246 ffv1.mkv)
    - Reversal original, 16mm, si., b&w and col. (Box 41, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0246)
  - Home movies, 1940s; 1450 film feet
    - Digital 2K+ preservation scan of reversal original RL10075-F16-0245 (Digital-materials RL10075-SET-0015, Video-file RL10075-F16-0245 ffv1.mkv)
    - Reversal original, 16mm, si., b&w and col. (Box 41, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0245)
  - Home movies, 1940s; 1000 film feet
    - Digital 2K+ preservation scan of reversal original RL10075-F16-0243 (Digital-materials RL10075-SET-0015, Video-file RL10075-F16-0243.mkv)
    - Reversal original, 16mm, si., b&w and col. (Box 41, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0243)
  - Home movies, 1930s-1940s; 650 film feet
    - Digital 2K+ preservation scan of reversal original RL10075-F16-0244 (Digital-materials RL10075-SET-0015, Video-file RL10075-F16-0244.mkv)
    - Reversal original, 16mm, si., b&w and col. (Box 41, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0244)
  - Home movies, 1930s-1950s
    - Digital 2K+ preservation scan of reversal original RL10075-F16-0248 (Digital-materials RL10075-SET-0015, Video-file RL10075-F16-0248 ffv1.mkv)
    - Reversal original, 16mm, si., b&w and col. (Box 41, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0248)
    - Thomasville holiday parade, 1959; 88 film feet, 0:03:16
      Scenes from a holiday parade in Thomasville, NC, November/December 1959. H. Lee Waters daughter, Mary Waters Spaulding, is on the "Miss Queen Piedmont" float. Miss America and Miss North Carolina are featured on additional floats.
      - Digital 10-bit 2K preservation scan of reversal original RL10075-F16-0252 (Digital-materials RL10075-SET-0023, Video-file RL10075-F16-0252.mkv)
      - Reversal original, 16mm, si., col, Kodak Kodachrome film stock, edge code = 1959. (Box 42, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0252)
  - Football, reel 1, circa 1940s; Severe acetate decay. (Box 39, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0239)
  - Football, reel 2, circa 1940s; Severe acetate decay. (Box 39, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0240)
  - Little League Baseball, original 16mm color reversal, circa 1955 (Box 37, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0236)
  - Out of the Shadows, children with disabilities in Davidson county, original 16mm, col., b&w, reversal, 1956 (Box 37, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0237)
  - Mooresville, 1937, provided by Mooresville Public Library. (Box 36, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0046)
  - Rockingham and Albemarle, undated, provided by the North Carolina State Archives (Box 36, Video-cassette RL10075-VHS-0002)
  - Siler City, 1937-1942, provided by Duane Hall. (Box 36, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0047)
  - Siler City, circa 1937, provided by Duane Hall. (Box 36, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0048)
  - Siler City, circa 1937, provided by Duane Hall. (Box 36, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0049)
  - Milo Holt interviewed by Duane Hall, 2008 November 9, provided by Duane Hall. (Box 36, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0050)
  - The cameraman has visited our town, by Tom Whiteside., 1989; 20 minutes (Box 33, Video-cassette RL10075-VHS-0003)
  - The movie man -- H. Lee Waters, "Assignment America," NBC Nightly News., 1990 January 19; 4 minutes (Box 33, Video-cassette RL10075-VHS-0004)
  - The preservation of the H. Lee Waters film known as "Chester, S.C." (October 1937)., 2007 June 11; 25 minutes (Box 33, Video-disc RL10075-DVD-0051)
  - The preservation of H. Lee Waters film known as "Chester, S.C." Julia Nicol emulsion peeling., 2009 November 19; 9 minutes
  - Animation test workprint, Duke logo and countdown leader for preservation reels., 2004 (Box 33, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0225)
  - Animation test negative, Duke logo and countdown leader for preservation reels. (Box 33, Film-reel RL10075-F16-0226)
  - Severely decayed film, Mayodan and Forest City, 1936-1942 (Box 40)
    Contains pieces of reels from Forest City and Mayodan, as well as several cans frozen shut with rust.
- Related Materials, 1936-2005
  - Advertisements, undated (Oversize-folder 1)
  - H. Lee Waters Movies of Local People Records, 1936-1942 (Box 34)
  - Advertisements, circa 1960s and undated (Box 34)
  - Notes, receipts, and correspondence, 1972-1974 and undated (Box 34)
  - Martin Johnson's master thesis, 2005 (Box 34)
  - Shot lists, undated
- Oral histories
  - Mary Waters Spaulding interviewed by Craig Breaden and Kirston Johnson, 2013-08-08; 01:02:17
    Mary Waters Spaulding talks about her father, H. Lee Waters, and growing up around her family's photography business in Lexington, North Carolina.
  - Tom Waters interviewed by Craig Breaden and Kirston Johnson, 2012-12-06; 00:49:49
    Tom Waters discusses the evolution of his father H. Lee Water's photography business in Lexington, how Waters came to make Movies of Local People, and the Waters' family life.